Guide to the Teresa Carmody Ladyfest 2000 Collection MSS.389
Fales Library and Special Collections
Teresa Carmody Ladyfest 2000 Collection
1999-2002
Fales Library and Special Collections
Carmody, Teresa
MSS.389
1.6 Linear Feet (2 manuscript cases and 1 flat box)
Ladyfest 2000 was a non-profit, community-based event organized by and for women to showcase, celebrate and encourage the artistic, organizational and political work and talents of women. Taking place in Olympia, Washington from August 1 to August 6, 2000, Ladyfest featured performances by bands, spoken word artists, and writers, as well as workshops, panels, art shows and dance parties. Teresa Carmody is a writer, and publisher of Les Figues. Carmody worked on the financial and legal aspects of Ladyfest—securing fiscal sponsorship from a 501(c)3 organization, and establishing systems for raising and processing funds. This collection represents her notes and associated documentation of the organizational aspects of Ladyfest.
Biographical Note
Teresa Carmody is a writer who was born in Western Michigan in 1973. She moved to Olympia, Washington when she was 18, where she eventually attended the The Evergreen State College, concentrating in cultural anthropology, Thai studies, and feminisms. She attended the first Ladyfest 2000 meeting in 1999; at the time, she was working as a grant writer and women's advocate at Safeplace. With Ladyfest budget co-coordinators Carrie Brownstein and Kanako Wynkoop, Carmody worked on the financial and legal aspects of the festival—securing fiscal sponsorship from a 501(c)3 organization and establishing systems for raising and processing funds.
In 2005, Carmody co-founded (with Vanessa Place and Pam Ore) Les Figues Press, a nonprofit, literary publisher of poetry, prose, visual art, conceptual writing and translation. Carmody holds an MFA in creative writing from Antioch University, Los Angeles, and is pursuing a Ph.D. in English/Creative Writing at the University of Denver. She is the author of the collection Requiem, and several chapbooks, including I Can Feel, Eye Hole Adore, and Your Spiritual Suit of Armor by Katherine Anne.
Related Materials
Ladyfest 2000 Collection (MSS.360)
Provenance
The Teresa Carmody Ladyfest Collection was donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections in 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical Note
Ladyfest 2000 was a non-profit, community-based event organized by and for women to showcase, celebrate and encourage the artistic, organizational and political work and talents of women. Taking place in Olympia, Washington from August 1 to August 6, 2000, Ladyfest featured performances by bands, spoken word artists, and writers, as well as workshops, panels, art shows and dance parties.
The inspiration for Ladyfest arose in part when some former members of the feminist Riot Grrrl movement were interviewed for Seattle's Experience Music Project's Riot Grrrl Retrospective oral history project in 1999. Looking back at their participation in Riot Grrrl, and in light of the sexual assaults that had happened at the 1999 Woodstock festival, they were motivated to create a festival that created a safe and inspirational space for women's performance and activism.
Ladyfest was organized and run entirely by volunteers. Initial meetings began in fall 1999. By the third meeting in January 2000, around 35 prospective organizers attended, and committees on Budget, Volunteer coordinating, Booking, Merchandise, Workshops, Visual Art, Performance, Documentation and Web Site Creation had been formed. The festival drew over 2,000 attendees, and included performances by Bratmobile, Sleater-Kinney, The Gossip and Cat Power. Workshops were given on auto mechanics, letterpress, gardening, and dismantling racism. Other events included a fashion show, a drag show, art openings, and a sewing circle. Ladyfest was a woman-run event, but all were welcome to attend. Events listed as "ladies only" were open to all women, including women who identified as men, and ladies who were born gentlemen. Since 2000, over 100 Ladyfest festivals inspired by Ladyfest 2000 have taken place worldwide, including in Australia, France, Indonesia, South Africa, and Switzerland. The meeting minutes have been archived at the Ladyfest website (http://www.ladyfest.org/planning/index.html#1230).
Scope and Content
The collection comprises documents created by Teresa Carmody and saved by her in the process of her volunteer work as an organizer of the Ladyfest 2000 festival. The records document her work as a member of the steering committee, and as a key organizer involved in the financial and fundraising aspects of the festival.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Series I: Files is arranged alphabetically. Series II consists of organizational documents Carmody kept in a binder, retained in their original order.
Community arts projects -- United States.; Riot grrrl movement.; Feminism; Feminist music; Workshops (seminars); Alternative spaces (Arts facilities).; Olympia (Wash.); LGBTQ+ activism; Performance art.; Women artists -- Exhibitions.; Artists -- Exhibitions; Ladyfest
- Series I: Files
  Scope and Content
  Series I: Files comprises all of the material kept by Carmody that was not housed in her organizational binder.
  - Administrative materials, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles, August 7 - September 1, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Card and photos - Tanner, Dana S., Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ladyfest: The Amalgamated Everlasting Union Chorus, August 5, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ladyfest Guide to Art Shows, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ladyfest: How to Zine, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ladyfest Performance Art / Spoken Word / Cabaret Program, August 1-6. 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ladyfest 2000 Presents Program Five: "Docu-go-go" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Map of Venues, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Non-Ladyfest Programs and Ephemera, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Official Program, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Passes, August 1-6, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pins, August 1-6, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Proposals / Drafts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stickers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tickets, August 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Tickets, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Binder
  Series II: Binder consists of organizational documents Carmody kept in a binder.
  - About Ladyfest, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Application to Form a Nonprofit Corporation, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Budget, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Budget, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Certificate of Incorporation as a Non-Profit Corporation, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Contribution Request Letter, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Donation forms, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fiscal Sponsorship, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fundraising, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Insurance Policy, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ladyfest Logos, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ladyfest Passes - Orders 97-160, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ladyfest Safety Information, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ladyfest Volunteer Flyer, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Meeting Minutes, June 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Performer / Volunteer List, June 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Planning, July - August, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Planning Notes, April - July, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Policies / Procedures, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Requests for Reimbursement (forms), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Safeplace, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Schedule, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sponsor Contracts, July - August, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sponsor Information, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - WACs / RCWs, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Women and Guitars at Ladyfest, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Oversize Materials
  - Assorted Newspaper Articles, July 27-28, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Assorted Newspaper Articles, August 1-7, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Assorted Newspaper Articles, September 12, 2001 - April 17, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin Board Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lady Quest poster, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Posters / Advertisements, August 2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ticket Designs, July 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)